Your Majesty
陛下
Why have you come here?
どうやってここに来たのですか
Rise
起きて
Your Majesty
陛下
You shouldn't move around
あなたは動かない方がいいです
It's cold now
今は寒いです
When the weather warms up later
しばらくして天気が暖かくなったら
I'll take you for a good walk
私はあなたをちゃんと一周案内します
What
どう
Is there something wrong with my body?
私の体に何か問題がありますか
Your Majesty
陛下
Of course there's nothing wrong with Your Majesty's body
陛下の体はもちろん何の問題もありません
You then
あなたに決めた
Take a team
一隊の人馬を率いる
With me
私と一緒に
Following behind Your Majesty
陛下の後ろについて行く
I promise you all
私は皆さんに約束します
Great Xuan has never forgotten the people of the north
大宣は一日たりとも北方の民を忘れたことがない
The royal army will recover the lost territories
王師は必ず故郷の地を取り戻すだろう
And restore peace to all
皆に平和な世界を取り戻す
This northern expedition
北伐のことですね
You're risking your life for it
自分の命を懸けるのか
Xuan Kingdom's greatest enemy
宣国の最大の敵
Has never been in the north
これまで北にはいなかった
Minister Chen means
陳相の意味は
What else does Your Highness want?
殿下他に何が欲しいですか
My friendship
私の友情
Does Your Highness dare to want it?
殿下それをお望みですか
We're not yet established
私たちはまだ足場が固まっていない
It's not yet time to move against them
まだ彼らに手を出す時ではない
Today the Ministry of Revenue calculated tax revenue
本日の戸部総合税銀収入
Totaling over 18 million taels
総計一千八百万元余り
Can shield Your Highness from wind and rain, block swords and spears
殿下のために風雨を防ぎ剣や槍を阻むことができる
It is Huan's fortune
それは桓の幸いです
Your Highness, this old minister finally sees you
殿下老臣はついにお目にかかることができました
If you stay away too long
あなたが外に長くいるなら
I'll name the child myself
私は自分で子供の名前を付けます
Speaking of defeat before the battle
戦う前にもう負けを言う
Since it's a fight to the death, I won't be a coward
死ぬまで戦いたいなら私はそんな悪党にはならない
Your Majesty, what do you need?
陛下何かご用ですか
Just order your servant to do it
直接私に行うように命じればよいのです
Five hundred it is
五百は五百
Five hundred men strike first
五百人中先に下手を行う者が強い
No more talk, come
彼と無駄話するな来い
Prince of Jin is rebelling
晋王の反乱
I am ordered to capture him
私は逮捕するよう命じられた
Surrender
手を出さずに降参する
And your lives will be spared
ポールたちの命
This northern expedition
今回の北伐
Our goal is to recapture Beiyu Pass
私たちの目標は北域関を奪還することです
Your Highness, Prince of Jin
晋王殿下
I'm Liu Dadao
俺はリュウダートウと呼ばれている
Commander of the Yong'an Garrison Left Army
乃永安守備左軍統領
Old brother, beat the drums for me
兄弟俺に太鼓を叩かせてくれ
Liu, Liu Nian
リュウ リュウネン
Your Majesty
陛下
When you were in Yiyang, you promised Grandfather
あなたは弋陽にいたときおじいさんに約束しました
To protect your servant for a lifetime of peace and joy
臣女の一生の平安と喜びをお守りください
Your daughter bids farewell
娘が別れを告げる
May Father Emperor take care of his sacred body
お父さまのご健康をお大事に願っています
Do you think the people kneel to you for nothing?
お前は民衆がなぜお前にひざまずくと思っているのか
They kneel to me, to Princess Xunyang
ひざまずけ私にひざまずけ彼女浔陽公主に
Can't catch a wolf without sacrificing the child
子供を手放せなければ狼は捕えられない
Your son is willing to be the vanguard
僕は先鋒になりたいです
Murong Cui of Yan Dong
燕東の慕容崔
By order of Princess Xunyang
浔陽公主の命によって
Come to reinforce
救援に駆けつける
It's all because of that Xuan Kingdom emperor
すべてあれは宣国の皇帝です
That got us into this situation
それで俺たちはこんな状況に陥ったんだ
At this point, only this last plan remains
ここまで来て残されたのはこの最後の一手だけだ
This plan, he taught it to me
この策はやはり彼が教えてくれたものだ
Chu Meng
楚蒙
Do you know why I must go on the northern expedition?
陛下がなぜ必ず北伐しなければならないか知っていますか
Your Majesty's achievements now surpass all past and present
陛下は今や古今を通じて功績が卓越しています
The northern expedition requires money
北伐にはお金が必要です
Requires bloodshed
血を流す必要がある
Requires the sacrifice of several generations to complete
何世代もの犠牲を払わなければ達成できないだろう
But I still must fight
しかし私はやはり戦うつもりだ
Because this cannot be measured by profit
この件は利益で計ることはできないため
Because Xuan Kingdom's people
宣国の民のために
They want to go home
彼らは家に帰りたいと思っています
They only recognize Xuan Kingdom as home
彼らは宣国という家だけを認めている
Look, look outside
外を見てごらん
Great victory, great victory
大勝 大勝
The royal army returns victorious
王師凱旋
Long live the Emperor
皇帝万歳
In your lifetime
あなたの一生
You achieved great merits
大きな功績を立てる
And committed great mistakes
大きな過ちも犯したことがある
Some call you a ruthless tyrant
誰かがあなたを手段を選ばない暴君だと非難している
But recovering the divine land
しかし神州を取り戻す
Is also an unparalleled achievement you created
それもまたあなたが築いた類まれな功績です
Standing on this mountaintop
この山の頂上に立って
You bear tens of thousands of people on your shoulders
あなたは数えきれない民を肩に背負っている
Subject to the judgment of later generations, history's pen is iron
後世の評判に任せよう歴史の筆は鉄のようだ
Along the way
一路行く
Love, hate, success, failure
愛 恨 成敗
All rest on your single thought
すべてはあなたの一念の中にある
The consequences of every choice
すべての選択の結果
You can only bear alone
あなたは自分で時間を潰すしかない
Some heroes are made by history
ある英雄は歴史によって作られるものです
While some heroes
そしてある英雄
Make history
歴史を築く
The ambition to look north at the realm
江山を北に望む志
Will forever exist because of you
あなたのために永遠に存在する